Amanda Visconti

AmandaVisconti@Gmail.com / 734-660-6602 / @Literature_Geek Portfolio: AmandaVisconti.com





I envision, prototype, and analyze user-driven digital interfaces, building on a strong research background (HCI M.S. and new Ph.D.) to innovate user experiences for social collaboration and learning.

SKILLS

Using a variety of design & development skills in the service of user-driven interfaces.

Web Design and Development. HTML5/CSS3/LESS, CMS theming and plugin creation: Drupal, Omeka, Wordpress, Mediawiki. Rapidly developing PHP and JS (strongest in context of CMSs). Server configuration, MySQL. Past Python and Google App Engine work.

User Research. User study metric creation, deployment, and analysis; custom site analytics including Google Analytics; nVivo; Gephi information visualization. Past R and SPSS experience.

Visual Design. Adobe Creative Suite: Illustrator, Photoshop, InDesign. Wireframing and rapid prototyping of working interfaces.

Interdisciplinary Collaboration. Git/GitHub, SVN, Basecamp, Lighthouse, Trello, Slack.

Clear Communication with Diverse Groups.

Academic and technical writing, user-friendly documentation, research blogging, teaching/training. Expert written and spoken communication between tech and non-tech audiences.

EDUCATION

Web development geek (8+ years) with a strong research background.

University of Maryland Ph.D. in Literature

(Digital Humanities, Interfaces for Social Learning) September 2010 – May 2015
Design, coding, user testing, and site analytics for the digital+social reading platform InfiniteUlysses.com.
The dissertation research around Infinite Ulysses lives at Dr.AmandaVisconti.com.

University of Michigan M.S. in Information

(Digital Humanities Human-Computer Interaction)

September 2008 – April 2010

Margaret Mann Award recipient. Master's thesis:
usability research on public use of digital editions has
had 1,600+ downloads from the repository since 2010.

St. Olaf College B.A., English

September 2004 – February 2007

LATEST PROJECT

Researching Digital+Social Learning Interfaces: Innovative Digital Literature Dissertation

User experience research via wireframing, prototyping, formal user testing, and site analytic data analysis. InfiniteUlysses.com encourages public participation in a platform traditionally aimed only at scholars (the digital edition) by testing adoption of mechanics from popular online communities like Reddit and StackExchange. The platform allows social annotation and personalization for the display of a huge quantity of annotations on a novel to fit each reader's needs and background. The *Infinite Ulysses* beta (developed as part of my dissertation) was visited by over 13,000 readers and cracked the top 20 on *Hacker News* during its first weeks of open beta.

EXPERIENCE

Research fellowship at one of the world's top digital humanities research centers

Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities; August 2014 - May 2015

Funded to spend a year creating *InfiniteUlysses.com*, an innovative platform for social reading and annotation of difficult texts that lets readers customize the annotations displayed to their needs using various social mechanics successful in nonacademic online communities such as Reddit.

UX design and development consulting: cultural archive interface, layered reading interfaces

Digital Humanities Initiative, Hamilton College; February - May 2014

TAPAS Project: TEI Archiving, Publishing, & Access Service; October – November 2013

Omeka/Neatline, Wordpress, and Fedora Commons research and advice for a digital archive. Developed stylesheets using CSS₃/LESS to improve display of TEI-encoded texts on a scholarly digital editing platform.

User testing, web design, & software documentation for archival digital forensics

MITH; August 2013 - May 2014

Wordpress and Mediawiki web design, site information re-architecture, audience-friendly software documentation.

Digital reading platform research and development

Editing Modernism in Canada (EMiC); April 2013 – March 2014

Server configuration, Drupal module development, web design, and audience-friendly Islandora documentation.

Digital humanities web development, design, and server administration

MITH; June 2011 – January 2013

CMS web development/design, long-term thinking for website maintenance, faculty/student documentation/training.

Instructor for honors college digital studies courses

MITH; University of Maryland English Department; August – December 2012; July 2011 – February 2012 Designed and taught three undergraduate honors and 200-level classes combining digital theory and practical tech labs on HTML5/CSS3, digital archives, social media for research, distant reading, remix culture, and copyright.

UX developer & edugame researcher/designer

National Science Foundation and University of Maryland; September 2010 - August 2011

Drupal development and design of feature-rich social community for players of an educational alternate reality game.

IMLS "Model Digital Humanities" internship MITH; April – June 2009

Omeka digital archive web design and development for a physical and digital collection of early e-lit and Web history.

Librarian *University of Michigan Medical School; April – October 2008*

Created an online-accessible catalogue, user-friendly library use and maintenance documentation, LOC numbering, and reorganization of the Huber Anatomical Donations Library.



RECENT INVITED TALKS and COLLABORATION

"Public → Participatory Digital Humanities: Designing the past & present of human culture for everyone" at the MIT Media Lab, May 2015

"Evaluating Digital Scholarship": Panelist at CUNY Graduate Center, April 2015

"Do read the comments: Designing digital editions for a public humanities conversation", Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, April 2015

Nebraska Forum on Digital Humanities: Digital Histories & Digital Authorship, *April 2014* "What if we build a digital edition and everyone shows up? Public Humanities, Participatory Design, and Infinite Ulysses"

One Week | One Tool DH Barn Raising producing Serendip-o-matic, August 2013 Digital tool for turning input text (bibliographies, articles, lyrics) into serendipitously related discoveries from online databases such as the Digital Public Library of America (DPLA) and Flickr. Development team member.

Speaking in Code Symposium Participant, *University of Virginia Scholars' Lab, November 2013* NEH summit for 30 accomplished digital humanities software developers to discuss expert knowledge.

Society for Textual Scholarship 2012 Conference Workshop Instructor, *May 2012* Designed and led workshop on the Omeka niche CMS at Society for Textual Scholarship 2012 conference.

"Infinite Ulysses: What if we build an edition & everyone shows up?" U. of Victoria, June 2013

RECENT PUBLIC RESEARCH PROJECTS & WRITING

Digital Humanities Now: Discover the Best in Digital Humanities Scholarship. Eleven posts from my LiteratureGeek.com academic blog are highlighted by the main aggregator for quality digital work in my field.

"Making the Digital Humanities More Open": Modeling Digital Humanities for a Wider Audience. Journal of Digital Humanities. (team-authored)

Co-authorship on six **research papers and conference presentations** on designing educational alternate reality games, with venues including the SIGCHI and Games+Learning+Society proceedings.

View DHQ: Gephi Info Visualization of Citation Networks. Gephi visualization of the journal *Digital Humanities Quarterly*'s citation networks towards identifying key digital humanities texts. Winner of an inaugural ACH (Association for Computing in the Humanities) Microgrant.

Digital Dos Passos (Digital Humanities Archive w/Innovative Interface). Omeka reading archive with custom non-linear entry into the collection.